Downloaded @ subs4free.club
I like to improvise.
I always think I like
to do things
as though I'm...
I'm playing jazz.
Try this, try that.
Okay, the sneakers
from Home Shopping.
I design them and I sell them.
Ordinary black denim jeans.
I'm a denim freak.
Reminded me of a railroad man.
When I was a kid,
I was a railroad buff.
These bracelets
come from Harlem.
These I have such a long time,
I don't even remember
where they came from,
but they were like
slivers of black,
so I love them.
And then these are just things
I've been collecting
over the years.
AnyWaY-
Another mad outfit.
These are my shoes,
smoking slippers.
Suede, embroidered.
This kind of tunic
is from the Mao people,
Chinese minority.
It had a big hood,
and I didn't like the hood,
so I made it into a collar.
And this is part
of my collection of amber.
And then bracelets
from all over the place,
including these ladybugs.
Okay?
I like to put
things together like this.
This is an old jacket
from, uh... Ungaro.
I love the way it's lined.
And these are Gianni Versace
trousers.
So they're kind of fun together.
I'll wear them
with a black turtleneck.
Just has to feel right with me.
Every time I do it,
I do a different way.
I like individuality.
So lost these days.
There's so much sameness.
Everything is homogenized.
I hate it.
Whatever.
- Albert?
- Yes?
Do you think we're demented?
So easy to amuse me.
I get more kick out of this
that costs $4 and change
than if my husband took me
to Harry Winston.
People interview me
and they keeping asking me
about all these rules,
and I say
I don't have any rules
because I would
only be breaking them,
so it's a waste of time.
With me, it's not intellectual.
It's all gut.
I see something,
"Oh, that'll go with this."
I'll try it on.
It's totally,
totally the involvement
and the process.
It's the process
I like much better
even than wearing it.
What could you do
on these three pieces?
Fifteen, 25, 30.
How about $25 for all three?
Can you do $20?
Mm, all right, why not?
I think it was
some very famous clothes horse
said the best thing
was getting dressed.
She didn't give a damn
about going to the party
or being at the party.
It was getting dressed
for the party.
And there's more truth
and poetry in that.
We are so pleased
to have Iris Apfel.
This event will show you
how she works
with people, their bodies,
and the way they should look
or the way they can look.
What brings you
to our fair shore?
I want something that
represents my personality
but is also classic,
so I need help.
There's somebody I've had
my eye on.
You, you, with the earrings.
Come here, girl.
- Oh.
- Oh, wowie-wow.
This was a Gaultier.
I thought it needed a belt.
So we added the belt.
The shawl is also an add-on,
but look at those shoes.
She looks very Vogue-y.
This was something that
when lris picked it out,
I thought she was a little...
I thought her 90 years
was showing.
I never would
have worn this myself.
I would have looked at it
on the rack and kept going.
But I love it.
This is my wild child.
She told me that sometimes
she has to go to occasions
where she has to be
a bit more sophisticated.
And I thought,
now that's a challenge,
to make her look sophisticated
and kooky at the same time
is not the easiest thing
in the world.
But we'll give it a try,
so see if you think
we've succeeded.
Francis, my gosh.
Wow.
Dress looks pure couture.
The necklace I think
is Missoni.
The necklace is spoken for.
I'm buying it.
Okay, baby.
I think you're in.
Thank you.
I was very much influenced
by my mother,
and my mother worshipped
at the altar of the accessory.
My mother could do tricks
with a scarf
that I've never seen
anybody else do.
It was during Depression days
that I grew up,
and my mother always said,
"Buy a good, simple
little black dress
and you'll always have
something to wear
because you can dress it up
or you can dress it down."
Thank you for sharing
your vision.
And on behalf of Loehmann's
90th year,
we would like to celebrate
your 90th birthday, too.
Oh, what a pretty cake!
What a pretty cake!
Oh, my God.
Looked like the eternal flame.
I had discovered Loehmann's,
it was in Brooklyn.
That was when Mrs. Loehmann,
the original...
who was absolutely a trip.
She looked like something
out of Toulouse-Lautrec.
And she would sit
on a high stool
like she was observing
a tennis match.
And she would look at what
everybody in the shop was doing.
And she used to fixate on me,
and she really made me
very uncomfortable.
And one day, she called me over,
and she said,
"Young lady,
I've been watching you."
She said, "Don't anybody...
You're not pretty,
and you'll never be pretty.
But it doesn't matter.
You have something much better.
You have style."
Iris is an artist.
What she uses all of her
clothing
and her accessories to do
is compose a new vision.
That for me is creativity.
Other people would say,
"Well, you know,
it's just getting dressed,
and we all get dressed."
Well, we all take snapshots
on our phone,
and that doesn't make it art.
The fact that she
combines everything,
what is nice, what is ugly,
what's cheap, what is chic.
So all these things,
and she just mixes that,
and she makes
her own style of that,
and that's really...
that's inspiration for me.
Her things are so special.
Everything Mrs. Apfel have
is gorgeous.
When I first met her,
there were all kinds of people,
all ages,
all walks of life,
all surrounding her.
She was so engaging
to everybody, you know?
And I could feel the pulse
of her life,
of her excitement
about living.
This is Iris Apfel,
and she is
a legendary collector,
um, of fashion.
Exhibits of her fashions
in museums
like the Metropolitan Museum
of Art's Costume Institute
drew record crowds.
And that was in 2005.
I went.
It was extraordinary.
And tell us what you're wearing
right now, Iris.
Oh, this actually
I bought many years ago
for my darling husband,
and...
You bought this shirt?
Yeah,
this was done by Versace.
He painted it himself.
It's leather.
So I grabbed it,
and I took it home.
And I gave it to him,
and he turned up his nose.
And he said, "Oh..."
lfis'husband
is sitting right here.
Carl is sitting right
here in the front row.
And Carl has pretty
fancy pants on.
Look at those pants.
They're from Etro.
I bought him those.
- Oh, are those new?
- Yeah.
Oh, okay. Very nice.
You're right with it, Carl.
Thank you, dear.
This goes back
to when the dinosaurs
were roaming the Earth,
1948.
Articles from The Times
and other newspapers.
This is what
I looked like then.
I never wanted a wedding.
I wanted to elope.
I said I'd rather have
the money.
But the parents
and the grandparents
wanted the wedding.
Our first date
was Columbus Day.
Thanksgiving, Carl proposed.
Christmas, I got blinged.
Washington's birthday,
we were married.
February 22nd.
There was no
Presidents' Day then.
It was a fairly small wedding,
I think 125 people.
But very posh.
The dress was pink lace,
and I'm really very practical,
So I wanted a dress that
I could wear after the wedding
and notjust put in a box.
I still have these shoes
sixty...
six and a half years later
They were pale pink satin.
They're back in style.
If you hang around long enough,
everything comes back.
This is ma and pa and moi.
No siblings.
There's Carl.
So gallant.
There was something about her
that just got into me.
It's always there.
Aw, my little pussycat.
And I figured he was cool
and he was cuddly,
and he cooked Chinese,
so I couldn't do any better.
But it's been one trip,
beautiful trip.
I trained him well.
And if she wants a child,
I'm it.
He's a handful.
The first piece I ever bought
was in Greenwich Village.
I was about maybe 11,
12 years old.
There was a little shop
in a basement
of one of those old-fashioned
kind of tenement houses
that had
the fire escapes outside,
and I'll never forget
that place
because I thought
it was Aladdin's cave.
There was this little man.
His name was Mr. Darris,
and he was threadbare
but elegant.
He always wore spats
and a monocle...
and I always tell everybody
he treated me
like I was a mini duchess.
I'd come in,
and he never seen a kid
be so interested
in all this junk before.
I fixed on a brooch.
I just thought
it was the cat's pajamas,
and I really lusted
after that piece.
So I finally saved up 65 cents,
and we haggled a little bit
over the piece.
I thought it'd be gone,
but fortunately for me,
it was still there.
Anyway, I bought it for
the magnificent sum of 65 cents.
He gave it to me.
I was so thrilled, my God.
You comfortable?
Yeah, fine.
ls it hard for you to do this?
Is it difficult?
No, not at all.
Honey, this is Harlem,
nothing's difficult.
Now this is...
there's a lot of African stuff,
- but the jewelry's great, Iris.
- Oh, let me see.
- Shall we go in? Okay.
- Oh, absolutely.
See, something white with...
Yeah, those are all,
like, jackets.
We'll go around there.
I've always said that
the population of Harlem
has much more style
than they do...
downtown,
they think they're stylish,
but they all were black,
you know?
It's not really style.
It's a uniform.
I used to come up here
on Sundays when I was a kid
and watch all the ladies
going to church.
Yeah, Sunday best.
And they had real style,
I thought.
And that sort of style
never goes out.
No, no, but it doesn't exist
much anymore.
But, you know, things change.
I hope. I hope.
I try.
- That's fun.
- The scarf?
- Yeah.
That's like a scarf
or a belt.
Oh, yeah.
How much?
That's 45.
That's a lot.
Careful, Iris,
you're on "Candid Camera."
I'm sorry, I'm cheap.
No! You're not cheap.
It's funny because
you find people think
you just acquire things,
but actually, that's not you.
No, it's hard work.
You really have to put
a lot of effort into it.
I know people who have
wonderful collections,
but it's different.
They go out to buy,
they go to...
Auctions and things
like that, yeah.
But everything I have,
I go out and find,
- which is not easy.
- No.
- I like that.
- That's beautiful.
I like it.
The color, everything.
So, monsieur,
how much are these ones?
Okay, the bracelet ten.
What I'll do, I'm going
to make you a deal.
We know you, okay?
Uh, take... I'll give you
$7 each for you.
And what can you do
on the coat?
The coat, we sell...
normal, we sell 125.
But I'll
let you have it 100.
- Okay.
- I know you.
I know you, queen.
We know you.
You can do better than 100.
- And the bag?
- This 85.
- Oh, you can do better.
- No, this 85.
You see, the tanner
took one day to make it.
- He's slow.
- Yeah. Yeah.
How did you get that?
I can't get those prices.
Oh, I'm very good.
I know.
flaughs)
Doing something creative,
taking your mind off things,
but that's how you shop,
and that's how you dress,
and that's how you think,
in that way.
Oh, yes,
I mean, it's fun.
Sometimes I really
don't feel well.
And I get in there,
it's like I'm 19 1/2.
I'm jumping around
and everything, and I'm so up.
When I crawl back to the car...
- I got my booty...
- How often do you need the fix?
Oh, I'd like to have it
more often than I get it.
Like how often, Iris,
once a week?
- Oh, I would love it once a week.
- Yeah.
I think what fascinates
me about Iris
is that she's the perfect
example of the intersection
of fashion
and interior design and art.
She's been exposed
to so many different areas
of creative worlds from being
an interior designer
to being involved
with Old World Weavers,
and Old World Weavers,
for those who aren't aware,
is this iconic company
that Stark then bought,
but their fabrics are in
some of the finest houses
that we photograph, you know,
still on a daily basis.
When we started
Old World Weavers, it came...
it was a crazy way, too.
We never intended to go
into the fabric bus...
Nothing I ever did
I intended to do.
Everything
just kind of happened.
She had a very
big decorating business.
I would go along with her.
I'd take my little toolbox,
hang the pictures.
And I got a kick
out of watching her
make something beautiful.
One day, I was looking
for a fabric that didn't exist.
I was doing a house,
and I wanted something special,
and then I remembered
that I had gone to school
with a young lady whose father
was supposed to be
a great weaver.
And I happened to run into her,
as luck would have it,
and she said, "Why don't you go
over to the mill and see Papa?"
So I did, and I brought
the design,
and he made it,
and it was a big success.
Everybody liked it.
And he said did I have
any more designs?
So after a while,
he asked if Carl and I
would be interested in going
into business with him.
And I thought
it would be fun.
We did exact reproductions
of 17th, 18th, 19th,
and early 20th Century fabrics,
and I would do my best
to get them to be as close
as possible to the original.
That's why we traveled
so much
because there is no one or two
mills that can do everything.
It's all very specialized.
They had done a lot of work
for different administrations
in the White House
and restored fabrics
and created special fabrics.
Well, uh... Barry...
the White House.
Was that from Barry...
We started when Truman
was here.
I know,
but how did they come...
I don't know,
they heard about us.
You see, the White House
has a fine arts commission.
Well, now,
can you make these changes
according to your own
personal tastes and desires?
Well, no,
I have a committee...
Oh, we had a problem
with Jackie.
Stop.
We're not supposed to talk
too much about the White House.
They get very upset.
My God, we did
so many restorations
in so many different museums.
I remember
I did Stephen Foster's
- My Old Kentucky Home.
- Did the Senate.
I did the Statehouse
in Mississippi.
Every great house
in America had our stuff.
I had a very
interesting clientele.
They didn't want to have things
that everybody else had,
so that started me traveling,
and I went twice a year
to Europe.
I was a busy bee.
And I would wear
three cameras.
I had a Nikon with a telly,
a Nikon normal,
and a Nikon wide-angle.
And the situations
would come up so fast,
I didn't have time
to change lenses.
So it was easier to have
the three cameras.
J' Hey, hey,
la la la la la J'
♪ Hey, hey I
When you'd get to know
some of the dealers like we did,
they'd open up places for us
like you never saw before.
They open at a certain hour,
and they close
at a certain hour.
Who do you think
was the last one? Iris.
I don't like to haggle
too much,
and I don't like to haggle
like some people do.
You have to know where to haggle
and when to haggle.
There are certain places
in the world
where you do a disservice
to the merchant
if you don't haggle.
If he says,
"This piece is $50,"
and you give him $50,
you have totally ruined his day
because he thinks, oh, my God,
if you're stupid enough
to give me $50,
right off the bat,
I should have asked you 150.
So it's part of the game.
J' Hey, hey,
la la la la la J'
♪ Hey, hey I
I didn't want to sell it,
and finally,
Starks made an offer
we couldn't refuse,
and I got more into all this
nutty stuff I'm doing now...
which is more fun.
Oh, I love this.
Here, let me show you.
It's great.
I have some weird jewelry.
Oh, they're wonderful.
Oh.
Oh, my goodness.
Okay, you have
a few sips of tea,
and then I'm going to
start my grooming.
Well.
Oh, thank you.
I need a Scotch after this.
Flaughs)
ls it tight or is it okay?
No, no, no, it'sjust
I look like a ghoul.
- You look amazing.
- Oh, come on.
Beautiful, like that.
Let me see you smile.
There you go, okay, one, two,
three, don't move.
Love it.
Now put your...
yeah, now that one.
Yeah, beautiful, I love that.
That's perfect.
There you go, yeah.
I love you right there.
Stay like that.
Now smile, again, a big smile.
One, two, three, great.
- This is fun.
- What?
- It is.
Okay, one, two...
eyes just a little bit...
Keep your face there
and your eyes... there you go.
One, two, three.
Awesome.
All right, thank you very much,
Iris.
Yay.
uaughs)
Have you ever thought
about having plastic surgery?
Oh, God, no.
Oh, I'm very opposed to that.
I think unless God gave you
a nose like Pinocchio
or you were in a fire or some
terrible thing, why mess?
Because you don't know
how it's going to come out.
You could come out worse
than when you started.
I mean, some very important
people I know go...
They come out
looking like Picasso.
It's not...
Why?
Why do you want to do it for,
a few wrinkles?
I see no reason for it.
I mean, maybe people
in show business
who are obliged
to look young or something,
but everybody knows
how old you are,
and then you have the
scrawny old hands
that don't go with your face,
and some people start
to fall down.
L... No.
I first met Iris
when a friend
who is an appraiser said,
"l've just met a woman
with the most remarkable
collection
of couture costume jewelry.
She probably has
one of the two best collections
in the United States."
That was the beginning.
I was working at F.l.T.
at the time,
and she was one of the great
lenders to our exhibitions
at F.l.T., the Fashion Institute
of Technology.
So we became friends,
and I saw her socially,
and even after we started
at the Met,
there was occasion
to borrow from her.
We had a show that was planned,
and at the very last minute,
there was something that
happened that it couldn't be...
We couldn't proceed,
and it was very late.
It was in the early summer.
And I thought, well,
we have to do a show
for the fall,
and what could it be?
I thought, you know, Iris
has this renowned collection
of costume jewelry that'll
be relatively easy to set up.
Why don't we do that?
As I was talking to her,
it occurred to me
we could do
something really fun.
Because instead
of having the jewelry
on these abstract mounts,
what we could do
is style them in a way
that they were Iris.
He said, "l think it would make
a much more interesting show
if you could show
the public
what you can do
with accessories.
How they can transform
an outfit.
Could you possibly spare
about five outfits?
You would have 100% authority
to accessorize them
any way you saw fit."
So I said, "Oh,
that sounds like fun.
What would you like?"
"Well, we don't know.
What have you got?"
And that opened
the Pandora's box.
When you think
about Iris' collection,
several rooms in her
Park Avenue apartment
are dedicated to her clothes.
Her closets
are double height.
That means two levels
of clothing jammed together
where you'll just see a sliver
of a Saint Laurent skirt
or an Ungaro blouse.
Lagerfeld piece.
Dior.
Galanos.
This is a shaman...
It's a Chinese shaman's...
jacket
But I'll wear it
as a cocktail outfit
with skinny pants.
She had
her mother's apartment,
which was filled
with clothing.
She had her apartment
in Palm Beach,
which was filled with clothing.
And so even for the person
who's put it together,
you know, what point
do you select this over that?
We knew that this
was going to be a show
that looked like nothing else
we had ever done.
They were very much afraid
because they had never done
a one-woman show ever.
It was like a written law.
If you're one-woman show
and you were not in the trade,
you ought to be dead.
Because
the previous exhibition
had fallen apart
and there was no sponsorship,
we had to make it
very close to the vest.
There was not
a lot of publicity.
It would have to be
word-of-mouth.
We didn't expect
that it would be
quite the phenomenon
that it was.
I don't know if there's been
any other show
that has relied so much
on word-of-mouth.
That's what surprised us,
people coming in
and leaving and saying,
"You have to see this show."
The response was remarkable.
I went back numerous times.
It was absolutely fascinating.
And then I'd overhear people...
the comments people made.
On a rare occasion,
I would comment
on their comments.
He'd tell me that people
would say, you know,
"Well, who is she?"
And they'd say, "Oh,
I don't know, she's dead."
So I told them,
"The next time you hear that,
tap the lady on the shoulder
and say,
'My auntie is very much alive.
She's just walking around
to save funeral expenses."'
J' New York,
New York, New York J'
J' Rock, shake to the beat J'
J' Rock,
shake in the streets J'
J' New York, New York,
New Yo-o-rk J'
These are mostly from Tibet.
They weigh a ton.
I wear them only
when I'm assured
that I can go home
in about half an hour.
Well, that's supposed to be me
atop this ostrich.
The jacket is made
of barnyard feathers.
I think it was
in American Vogue
that I saw the first thing
about Iris.
I think that for her, also,
the exhibition at the Met
was a very big change
in her life.
And I'm an octogenarian starlet.
I think that's fun.
J' See happy people dancing
to the funky New York beat J'
I began to be,
in a small way,
a public person.
I mean, I was always known
in the trade,
in my interior design,
and called upon for quotes
and written about, but, I mean,
not to the degree...
I mean,
this was an avalanche.
J' Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa,
New York J'
I think part of the reason
they responded to it
was this feeling
that it was play.
Here was somebody who was just
having a great deal of fun.
Life is gray and dull,
and you might as well have
a little fun when you dress
and amuse people.
Do you like that?
Did you hear what she said?
Yeah.
flaughs)
The show changed
a lot as it moved.
The next show in Palm Beach
just flowed.
There were seven
contiguous galleries,
and you walked
from one to another.
Then I went to the museum
on Long Island,
in Nassau County,
and then Peabody Essex
was really the climax.
It was really beautiful
because they have huge,
soaring ceilings,
and they did
a really great job.
I'm sure that the reason
my shows were so successful
was that they provided fantasy
or it provided some glamour.
There are a lot
of explanations.
Maybe people caught up with me.
Maybe I was too far ahead.
Maybe people
are looking for something
that's missing in their lives,
because as much as people say
they don't want to be bothered,
I think
they really yearn for it.
J' I love New York J'
J' I love New York... J'
Your audience
is waiting over here.
I've never seen someone
look better
in a pair ofjeans
than Iris.
I know, I've been
watching her for years.
It's nice to meet you.
Jenna wants to meet you.
Jenna's the president
of J. Crew.
Oh!
You are the most chic,
most beautiful,
most incredible woman
I have ever seen.
I've been such a fan of yours
for so many years.
It's such an honor to meet you.
Well, thank you,
I'm so impressed to meet you.
Oh, please, please.
Oh, I mean...
Not even close.
It's an honor.
Thank you.
And the accessory designer
of the year is Alexander Wang.
And right here, guys.
Hold up the award
and straight ahead this way.
It's a pleasure to meet you.
Great meeting you, too.
- I'm a big fan.
- Oh, thank you.
You look so good tonight.
Thank you, my goodness.
From a handsome
young fella, wow.
I think people
can't even imagine
having that kind of a life
that she has,
and she loves
every fucking minute,
and even if she's
complaining about it,
which he does every single time
I talk to her...
She'll say, "Oh, my God,
I'm so exhausted,"
Like, the conversations
are the same.
It's like I'll call her,
she'll be like, "l'm so tired.
I was just on TV, and then
I'm doing another interview."
And I'm like,
"lris, you love it."
She's like, "l don't love it."
I'm like,
"No, Iris, you love it."
She's like, "l kind of like it."
flaughs)
Oh, wow.
Oh, my goodness.
Oh, that's great.
Oh, I love it.
That's terrific.
Oh, how good he is.
Terrific.
He takes good care of me.
Then take a picture of Desi
taking a picture.
Iris became one
of my favorite models,
and so I said,
"Well, Iris,
I've got to photograph you
at your house."
So I went over to their place
in Palm Beach,
and their apartment
was like this total trip.
It was like a fantasy,
all these little games
and things and animals
that barked...
Dogs that bark, you know?
That's Gussie.
Gussie is a bar.
Her wing goes up,
and her belly
is full of booze.
And Kermit decided
he'd like to live here,
and he's become
a terrible lush.
See how tipsy he is?
And these are
some of my Kachinas.
I've had a number
of museum shows with them.
These are some
of the little teddy bears.
I like him.
He's from the Ritz in Paris.
Stay there, boy.
We used to go
to Santa Fe every summer.
And many, many years ago,
I started to buy this kid
when he was maybe 14 years old
and starting.
He's a Navajo,
and his sister used to help him
dress the figures.
I used to buy one or two
every year,
and when I took them all out,
I never realized
this kid is hung up
on transportation
Because every one of these
is going someplace.
They keep
the Christmas ornaments,
the Christmas lights on
for almost six to eight months,
so it's kind of always Christmas
there.
All aboard!
Did you ever see
Christmas trains?
Pardon?
Did you ever see
Christmas trains before?
No, no.
It's the most perfect house
for two children.
All right.
Okay, we'll speak
in the morning.
Thank you.
They throw out
more food than I ever saw.
There's no more?
There's still another one.
It's not my yogurt.
- Huh?
- It's not mine.
Then get two.
Two is more than enough.
Okay, have a good day.
Yeah.
Thanks, David.
You like this Carl?
- Yeah.
- Huh?
- It's De La Renta.
De La Renta
Do you like it?
Oscar should like it.
What's not to like?
Money, money, money.
J' That's where my money goes,
to buy my baby's clothes J'
Oh, well.
Either that or Uncle Sam.
Rather give it to her.
- Isn't this fabulous?
- What?
- Look at this.
- That's wild.
I love this the best.
That's a fun thing.
I'll take this one.
Should I get the other one?
- Huh?
- You like the other one?
Yes, dear.
I like the poor bastard
there on the back.
You never know what's going to
happen with this child.
Surprise, surprise.
It's very good.
It's not a dull marriage,
I can tell you that.
Come, let's walk.
How much?
$2?
Is this yours?
I wonder if they have
any long-sleeve.
That's fun.
It's $30, though,
and it doesn't look good on you.
Doesn't look good?
Okay?
This one.
He likes that.
- Like it?
- I love it.
Make a deal.
Make a deal, McNeal.
ls it heavy?
Not bad, no.
It's all right, sweetheart.
I'm getting used to it.
You have to pay
for being stylish.
It doesn't affect
my brainpower.
Oh, could you order me...
because I have...
the Wall Street Journal?
Yeah, because there's
a piece about me.
Day in the life of.
Okay? Thank you.
- And that's for Saturday only?
- Right, thank you, thank you.
Hello?
It's Iris Apfel.
I'm in Palm Beach.
Yes, yes, we had our interview
this morning.
Monday, we'll be
all day at the doctor's.
We have to go for a whole bunch
of eye tests.
How many phone calls do
you think Iris gets in a day?
Oh, Lord,
sometimes about 50 or more.
I mean, back to back,
the cell ringing and
the house phone ringing.
You can't keep up
with this phone, you can't.
You got something.
Where's my phone?
Oh.
J' Fly me to the moon J'
- Take that hat off him.
- No!
It's a terrible hat.
What's the matter
with the hat?
Iris, the hat's holding
my head on straight.
Oh, excuse me.
J' What's it all about, Alfie? J'
Your voice is worse than mine.
Nezzie has a beautiful voice.
This is Nezzie.
She's the chief of this house.
Look at her slippers
she makes.
Very talented wife.
I think I'll keep her.
Trade-in value's not so high.
flaughs)
Oh, well.
Have all your things set up.
These are how many minutes
we're spending on each item.
- Mm-hmm, may I sit down?
- Yes, you may.
- Those are drop-dead.
- Yeah.
That looks good.
I like these together.
Everybody like these
together?
See, if you do
something like this,
it starts to get a look.
Looks good.
We'll take that picture.
And then just one last thing,
and then we're done.
I think that's
such a great scarf.
Mm-hmm, it's fun.
- All your stuff is fun.
- Well, thank you.
- Everybody loves it.
- Yeah.
Stand by.
Well, good morning.
She is here, the rare bird
herself of fashion,
the icon herself,
Iris Apfel.
Over 75 years of all of that
influence in the fashion world,
interior designing,
accessories
exclusive to you on HSN,
and it is such a treat.
That's so nice to hear.
Makes a girl feel like
there's still a chance.
Flaughs)
Definitely.
So tell us about these again.
You don't do anything petite.
NO' no' no' no' no!
I like big and bold
and lots of pizzazz.
And it's about color coming
into the season, isn't it?
Absolutely,
color is so important.
I mean,
color can raise the dead.
For many of us, you give
us the freedom, you know,
step out of the box
a little bit.
That's what life is all about.
If you're just going
to sit there
and do the same damn thing
all the time,
you might as well
jump into the box yourself.
Flaughs)
Exac... you heard it here.
It's exactly right.
Did we sell well?
You know, I don't know.
I was watching.
I wasn't looking at the numbers.
- How did it go?
- You looked fantastic.
My computer kept
freezing up on me, but...
- But you looked fantastic.
- Well, thank you.
Thank you, great job.
Thank you.
And it sold out.
You can't wear it any more.
This one did?
I'm wearing it.
Hi, I'm going in style.
In the '40s, I was probably
the first woman to wearjeans.
All of a sudden,
I had a vision.
I said I wouldn't it be
wonderful
if I had a big gingham...
this sounds crazy.
It was.
A big gingham...
a big gingham turban
and very large hoop earrings
that I could wear
with a nice crisp shirt
and blue jeans?
They said to me,
"Don't you know
young ladies
do not wearjeans?
What's wrong with you?"
And I said, "But I want a pair.
I need a pair."
"Well, we're very sorry.
We can't help you."
Well, they were just so mean.
They threw me out.
But when I want something,
I'm like a dog with a bone,
so I went back.
I went back
a couple of times,
and finally,
I guess in an effort
just to get me off his back,
the owner called me
on the telephone...
Oh, it was maybe about
five or six weeks
of really hard work
on my part...
And he said
he had mail-order...
had mail ordered me
a pair of boy's jeans,
and they fit.
So I put the outfit together,
and it was really smashing.
It really was.
Do you think, Iris, like,
for you, did...
Because for me,
I became confident
once I, like,
pretended I was
and forced myself into wearing
things I was shy about.
Did it come after
for you or...
I can't remember
that far back.
Hey, sweetheart,
you look beautiful as ever.
Thank you.
I'm vertical, so I'm so happy.
Oh.
flaughs)
You know why I think
you did this film?
- Why?
- Because he's very handsome,
and I think
you really had a crush on him.
- Everybody does.
- I know.
Remember the evening
we went to that party,
and there were a number
of elderly ladies,
and they were like...
all over Albert.
- Yeah.
- My God. He was like a magnet.
Uaughs)
Isn't it amazing now
how many designers don't sew?
They don't sew.
They don't drape.
- They're media freaks.
- Right, exactly, yeah.
It's unbelievable.
See, these new kids
go to the vintage shows,
and they buy a few pieces,
and they change a button or two,
and they knock it off,
and it's crazy.
Theyjust have no sense
of history
and no curiosity
about anything.
When you were, like,
growing up,
didn't you have a sense
of history just from reading
- and looking at things...
- Oh, of course.
Listening to music
and everything?
I had a great sense of history,
and I realized
that everything
is interrelated
and that politics and science
and economics and fashion
and all that are one
and part of the same,
and I applied it...
I know if you look at a dress,
it's affected
by all those things.
I mean, you can almost tell what
was going on at that period.
You know,
I've never heard you say,
"l don't like the way
that person dresses."
- I can't sit in judgment.
- Right, exactly.
- It's not my business.
- Right.
If they're happy that way...
you know,
It's better to be happy
than well-dressed.
Flaughs)
Exactly. That's so great.
Nice.
- Hi.
- There she is.
Hi.
Oh, how cute.
Welcome, you're so...
Okay, Iris,
after this is all laid out,
I am officiallyjealous.
I have a lot
of catching up to do.
- No, I mean...
- This is a drop in the bucket.
Okay, so Iris and everybody,
can I tell you what we set up?
All the accessories are here.
All the shoes
are down on the floor.
I'm not sure if we're going to
get that far, but they're there.
We dressed several mannequins
here with almost everything...
Right behind you.
...almost everything.
- This one I...
- You tell us what to do.
And this I thought
with the brown pants.
- The brown pants?
- Yeah, that's so you don't...
- You don't see anything else.
- Okay.
And then I have some jewelry.
And I have those Missoni shoes.
And then I put this...
- That on top of that?
- Yeah.
Oh, that's the secret for
how you get some of your depth.
Beautiful, so sculptural.
- It spoils the...
- The line of the jacket?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
Is she dragging it?
Yeah, that's what I mean,
something like that.
Dragging it along kind of?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah,
I love that.
- Because we can do that.
- That's what I meant.
We like that kind of rhythm
anyway to break it up.
So it'll go down here,
okay.
- We think on the same beam.
- See?
We could do, you know,
glitz and bling
if you wanted to,
or we could just do
this kind of...
Lots and lots of dots, right.
Iris, that looks pretty great.
You know you could do...
maybe want to add this to it?
Oh, I see how this works.
Some people might have assumed
this was just one piece.
- People usually do.
- But no, you're making it.
What you have to do...
see, I used to do things
with antique bits and pieces,
and what I was so proud of
was they looked like
they were born that way.
They didn't look like
they were put together.
I hate when
it looks put together.
Oh, you want this
on the top here.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
Or you think maybe
too much for the window?
No! no! no, "Q, "C.
You know the secret
behind doing windows?
- What, too much?
- No, it's never too much.
You always do
the most outlandish.
Oh, well, that's for me.
You want to give me a job?
Iris,
let me ask you a question.
Do you have glasses to spare?
Well, for the window,
I guess I have a few pairs.
I don't know how many I have.
We were thinking we might
do this sort of thing.
See it, Linda, the mask there?
Might do something like that.
- This is a classic...
- I kind of like the glasses.
The mannequins
could be holding something.
I think it's a little chicer
just with glasses
instead of with...
you know what I mean?
We know it's Iris
just by the glasses.
Let's just...
but these would break, I guess.
Here, I'm not going to
let go of them.
Let's see the...
Let's try this girl here.
Gee, I wonder who this is.
The point of this
is just a little thing.
I wanted to show sort of
all your different jobs,
that you have
more jobs than anyone.
Oh, I love that.
I love that.
Isn't there sound?
How do we tell the man
that there's no sound?
Oh, okay, thanks.
Can you start it over?
We have something
really big for you
- to surprise you with.
- For me?
- Yes, absolutely.
- Oh, wow.
There's some noise
coming from the bag.
o“, my God! oh!
So you can use this
to shop with you
when you go to Whole Foods
to buy your forbidden rice.
Oh, that's fabulous!
- That's going to be in the stores.
- No.
- Yeah.
- Big like this?
- Big like this.
- Oh, Albert, look at that.
- Oh, my God.
- We're excited about it.
Oh.
Oh, I can't believe it.
Oh, my God.
I love you, Rory.
You've been so kind
and gracious to me.
My God.
If somebody could
just open the door?
I'll get it.
I heard your other
collection is sold out.
Sold out.
Yeah, the Home Shopping.
Yeah, it was so exciting.
Were you on it yourself
selling it?
I was supposed to,
and I was in the hospital.
Ijust had surgery.
So they asked me
if I would talk,
and I said yes,
and I summoned all my energy,
and I did two shows.
I guess it was about
half an hour each.
And I was very...
You know, it was very exciting,
and the next... for two days,
I couldn't get out of bed
I was so drained.
Carl doesn't know
I had hip surgery.
He doesn't know
my hip was broken.
Really?
How did you do that?
Well, I didn't do it.
Nezzie did.
Because Carl
is very devoted to me,
particularly now that
he isn't feeling well,
and she said if she was going
to stay with him,
she couldn't tell him
because he'd go bananas.
And he really was so upset
that I wasn't at home.
- He knows I fell...
- Where did he think you were?
No, he knows I fell.
He was sleeping
when it happened.
But when he got up...
what was I going to do?
I was trying to wait
till the next day,
but the head of NYU,
the head honcho
is a good friend,
and he said, "You're crazy.
You have to come immediately,
and you have to come
in an ambulance."
So I had to call the ambulance,
and I thought, "Oh, my God."
But God was good,
and they sent me
the two most delicious guys.
They were big hunks, but they
were so sweet and so kind.
And I explained the situation,
and they were, you know,
kidding around
with Carl and whatnot,
and they got me out.
He thinks I fell...
He knows I fell
and hurt my leg badly,
but he doesn't know
I broke my hip.
He doesn't know what happened.
So we're always together.
We work together
and everything else,
so he's used
to having me around.
He's older than I am,
well, so it was very sweet.
You're very sweet together.
AnyWaY---
Have you met...
This is the Maysles crew.
- No!
- I'm Katie.
Katie, I'm Nancy.
Nice to meet you.
- Sean.
- Sean, nice to meet you.
And this is Albert Maysles
himself.
Hello, Albert,
so nice to meet you.
You want a nibble?
Help yourself.
- Yes, yes.
- Albert, you want...
I'm okay.
I had some breakfast.
- Sweetie, you want some?
- We're okay, thank you.
Greetings,
and welcome to the launch
of the UT in NYC program.
It is my pleasure
to introduce Mrs. Iris Apfel,
our tour guide
and visiting professor
for the week
in New York City.
Mrs. Apfel?
I have brought you
14 eager students
from the University of Texas.
Good, well, I don't want
to waste any time
because we have
a lot of things to do.
And the reason I chose this
was because I've had occasion
in the last couple of years
to work with students,
which I never did before,
and I find that, unhappily,
they may be very well-trained
in their craft,
but they haven't got a clue
as to the outside world.
So the sage has spoken.
Everybody faints
when they hear the itinerary
because it's really...
I must say,
they're all offbeat fields
like licensing and styling
and things that kids
don't think about as fashion.
They just think
it's not glamorous,
but it's important.
I mean, all the great
handcrafted trades
are going down the tubes.
Some have already gone.
And then there's nobody left
to teach them,
and you'll have all kinds
of machine-made junk.
Listen up, everybody,
this wonderful, wonderful man
is going to talk with you.
He is in my opinion,
and I think not only mine
but everybody else's,
the king of the runway,
and he comes
from a long tradition
of embroiderers and beaders.
So listen, he's going to
tell you wonderful things.
You have to keep your eyes open
for anything and everything.
Like me flying, going to Miami,
I look down from the plane,
and I see fields of...
you know, fields.
It looked like a...
like an amazing pattern.
I drew it up,
and it's in one of my dresses.
Now it's up to you
as a designer.
What are you inspired by?
And I think
whatever feeds you...
You could be curious about math,
you could be curious
about science,
about fashion,
you could be curious
about anything,
but ultimately, what drives you
and makes you better
is learning something
you don't already know.
I could never be
a good friend of anybody
who wasn't curious or didn't
have a sense of humor.
I think those are the two great
gifts that I got in my cradle.
I really believe that.
People always love enthusiasm,
and I think that, in the end,
New York is about work
and getting a job done.
So it's great if you're
a cute girl in a cute dress
and want to be
on the red carpet, but really,
if you mean business,
New York is the place for you.
If you mean business,
people will
take you seriously, I think.
It's very important to me
that my program continue.
It's going gangbusters.
The kids are now fighting to get
in, and the school shows no...
I mean, unless it falls
by the wayside
and they can't get
anymore funding...
I mean,
I can't do this forever,
but I'm sure they'll be able
to get somebody else.
Awesome, thank you.
You never had children.
No, we never wanted to.
I mean, not that I...
but you can't...
I learned a long time ago you
can't have everything,
and I wanted a career,
and I wanted to travel,
and my mother...
I know how much I resented it.
She had stopped for a while,
and then when I was like ten
or 11, she went back,
and I was very upset.
Very upset.
I felt I was...
I mean, it was stupid,
but I felt I was being
abandoned,
so I said I didn't want to have
my child raised by a nanny.
And you can't do everything.
It's impossible.
Something has to give.
And sometimes it's you.
Well, I haven't had a
chance to go through anything.
Yes.
Logistics, logistics.
Okay. There we go.
Galliano's pieces
are fantastic.
Yes.
This is spectacular.
The Peabody Essex Museum
hosted Iris' exhibition
"The Rare Bird of Fashion"
in, um...
'09.
And then when the
exhibition came to the museum,
we invited Iris and Carl,
of course,
to be part
of the installation.
And so I learned
that Peabody
had a fashion collection,
but it more or less stopped
at the time that mine begins.
So we decided
that it would be a nice fit,
and that I would,
little by little,
give all the stuff
to the museum.
So we started last year.
They got 80-odd pieces
last year.
Yes, mm-hmm.
Probably get another batch,
and will keep going.
Oh, those are trousers.
Oh, look at that.
Oh, with a matching coat.
What an interesting
color combination.
This is a very personal
collection.
This is mine, and I didn't
buy it to impress anybody.
I bought it
because I liked it.
And I wore almost everything.
Some things I wore to pieces.
This is the green...
This is the green one.
I was collecting
church vestments at one point.
So with this one,
I found a pair.
I took the pair,
and I cut it apart,
and I made a pair of trousers.
- This has a number.
- What is that?
It's a black, white,
or blue...
- With fringe.
- Oh, no, it's dark blue.
Oh, that's a gorgeous fabric.
That is a fabric to die for.
Yeah, as if there aren't other
to-die-for fabrics here.
But this one is very...
But it's interesting
to see which ones
you get really excited about.
Look at this.
- Oh, wow.
- It's woven.
It's a velvet
and then the lace, wow.
It's quite the combination.
But look at how it's threaded
up through with the fringe.
Where did you find this?
Here or...
No, you' don't find
anything like this here.
Somebody once told me,
and it's so true,
you really don't own
anything while you're here.
You just rent,
so sometimes,
it might be nicer to
see where it's going
than to not know who gets it,
so I'm happy to do it.
How do you choose
what to give away?
It's not easy.
Does it keep you up?
Oh, God, no.
No, I have more important things
to keep me up at night.
No, no.
Well,
now I have to ask what...
What keeps you up at night?
Oh, I mean...
Matters of health
and things like that.
Things
that are really important.
Mm-hmm.
I mean, as you get older,
you realize
that all these other things
are just...
Iris,
just looking over here?
How many people have been
in here before, Iris?
Not too many.
I don't let anybody in here.
Trying to get it
a little organized.
Great.
Uaughs)
Do you want me
to hang this somewhere?
- Just stick it here.
- Okay.
I have two more hangars
of items.
Thank you.
It's a system until a lot
of people stick their noses in,
and then it gets
all fucked up.
Put it here.
Okay, and then
this J. Crew dress.
- Put it here.
- Okay.
Look at that coat.
Hi.
How are you?
My beautiful child.
How are you, pussycat?
I made it.
Are you all right?
Are you okay?
I don't know.
Somebody's stealing my breath.
Be quiet.
Relax, relax, relax.
What's that cousin's name
with two kids up there?
Carl, just relax.
Don't talk.
Catch your breath.
My aunt rarely relaxes,
and I think that's kind
of a fault on occasion.
I think sometimes she should
slow down, and I ask her,
or I kind of even insist,
that she do a little bit,
rests a little bit more,
but it's not her personality.
She's even said
that when she's not busy,
she can get depressed.
She's not at all
a depressive person,
but I can understand
that her personality
is to keep moving,
keep busy, keep occupied,
keep creative, keep productive,
and that's her life,
and it has always been
her life.
Oh, I like being active.
I like being in the world
and of the world,
and everybody has to do it
in his or her own way.
I think I told you this
about my mother's friend.
When you would say,
"How are you feeling today?"
She'd say,
"Well, to tell you the truth,
when I get up in the morning,
everything I have two of,
one hurts,"
and that's the way it is.
When you're older,
a lot of people
just give into that,
but unless it's something
really serious,
but if it isn't,
you just have to push yourself,
and then you go out,
and you start to do things,
you forget about yourself.
Otherwise,
you can just sit there
and brood all day long.
I mean, you cannot do
what you did.
People say what an energy
and everything I have,
but it's nothing
like what I used to have.
Now I get tired.
I'm ready for the voyage.
- Hi, sweetie.
- Hi, darling.
How are you?
I don't know. Vertical.
I'm vertical.
- Where you going?
- Back to work.
Back to work?
Make sure they take it easy
with you, okay?
- Yeah, they're good people.
- Okay.
Hi.
Okay, we're off and running.
- Right here.
- Right here?
Yeah, that's the elevator.
Not a friendly policeman.
Hello?
I had a very
interesting clientele.
They didn't want to be dragged
from showroom to showroom
and have things
that everybody else had,
so that started me traveling,
and I went twice a year
to Europe
and each time took at least
a 40-foot container
besides going to all
the auctions and estate sales
and everything else.
That has to go.
That one goes.
- And, uh, this piece goes.
- That one's going.
Then, uh...
And two more pieces over there.
Oh, a lot of pieces.
I believe this one goes.
That big long bench goes,
yes, yeah.
It wasn't easy
to part with these things
because they have so many
memories connected with them.
I'm sorry to see them gone,
but c'est la vie.
They don't do me
any good here.
They don't do anybody any good,
and they're so beautiful,
they might as well brighten
somebody's life,
and frankly,
I can use a few more shekels.
- This is 750.
- What were you thinking?
- What?
I don't know.
I have to check. I really do.
Oh, my God.
Oh, my God,
it's one of those panels.
Mm-hmm.
Wait, there was something
I had to show you.
Hmm.
That's really different.
I thought it could be
a wall hanging,
or it could even...
maybe a bed thing
- because that could tuck under.
- Hang over the bottom?
Mm-hmm. Yeah, definitely.
0K3)!-
When I didn't know any better
and we first went to Paris
years and years ago
right after the war,
the dealers would say,
"You must come
early in the morning to my..."
they called them "my box,"
and you'd have to get there,
like, 4:00 in the morning
with a big searchlight,
and it was always damp
and cold and miserable.
And we did that for a while,
and then my husband said to me,
"You know,
this is really stupid.
You don't buy
what other people buy,
and almost everything you buy,
you always say,
"lt has to have
my name on it.
If it's got your name on it,
baby,
it's going to be here
at 11:00 in the morning."
So that's what we continued
to do, and it worked.
I still occasionally miss
that terribly.
It's definitely
the end of an era.
It's the end of another life.
It took me a long time.
You have
to get yourself psyched.
Especially a collection
like that, you know,
every piece has a memory
because most of them
were bought on trips
or different occasions.
My accountant said to me,
"Just think of all the money
you would've saved if you
had done this years ago."
Well,
but I wasn't ready.
I feel that for everything
there is a season.
And I suppose that when I put
the last key in the door,
I'll go home
and get hysterical.
Right now, I'm managing.
You got a birthday
coming up, huh?
Yeah, August 4th.
That scares the hell out of me.
What am I going to do
for an encore?
Ah, me.
Well, if you made it
this far, you can go further,
that's my idea.
Happy birthday.
You're looking great.
I love your pants.
I can't tell you how happy...
Dr. Pritchard took care of us
for over 40 years.
Jenna, oh, I'm so happy
to see you.
Hi, how are you?
Happy birthday, kid.
Carl doesn't like
to talk too much,
so he wants me to say
a word or two or four.
Go ahead.
He wants to thank everybody
for coming.
It's so nice.
We're so pleased
that you're all in our life.
You've been so generous
in sharing
so many wonderful things
with us all these years.
And Carl feels the same way,
and he's very happy
to be sailing
into his second century.
And he has...
He has a word of advice
to the guys.
He says,
in the words of my grandpa,
"A woman is
as old as she looks,
but a man is never old
until he stops looking."
Blow, Carl.
I want to do more things
in this life
with my child bride.
And if the Lord lets me do it,
I'll sure enjoy it.
Why not?
You got one trip.
Now, you see?
She thought
I was getting chilly.
She's right.
I never felt pretty.
I don't feel pretty now.
I'm not a pretty person.
I don't like pretty.
So I don't feel badly,
and I think it worked out well
because I found
that, for instance,
all the girls that I know
who were very pretty girls
and got by on their looks,
as time went on
and they faded...
They were nothing.
And they were very,
very disappointed.
When you're somebody
like myself,
in order to get around
and be attractive,
you have to develop something,
you have to learn something,
and you have to do something.
So you become
a bit more interesting.
And when you get older,
you get by on that.
Anyway, I don't happen
to like pretty.
Most of the world
is not with me,
but I don't care.
Okay, excuse me.
Help yourself.
Have anything you want.
J' Hey J'
Okay, you readY?
This is
your Halloween costume.
Can you see?
Oh, my God. Oh, my God.
Poor children.
Look at that.
How crazy is that?
And people buy that?
Oh, my God.
The Council
of the city of New York
is proud to honor
legendary taste maker,
fashion icon, businesswoman,
interior designer,
and style maverick
Iris Apfel.
Today, Mrs. Apfel remains
a popular, outspoken,
ornate muse
for fashion designers
and artists of all kinds.
Thank you all
for this humbling honor.
It's really remarkable
that I've been able to live
and practice
my assorted madness
in this most
multileveled city in the world,
and I thank you,
and I thank all the residents
who have supported me
and made me what I am today,
a geriatric starlet.
I like yourjacket.
Groovy.
I would be happy
to give you this one.
Oh, fantastic.
Voilé.
You'll be a Western...
a Western dude.
A Western dude, yeah.
- Voilé.
- Rhys, the dude.
Look at these.
I love these.
I think they're...
This has
a double-face cashmere,
and it actually comes apart
so you can wear...
this by itself.
Like a stripper.
Is that supposed
to keep me warm?
I don't know.
It's Irish wool.
Let's see.
How much does it cost?
No price.
Well, if you're interested,
tell me.
I'll see if I can help you
with a deal.
He was the original RCA Victor.
He loves jewelry,
and I couldn't get
anything to fit him,
he has such a fat neck.
And I told him
if he went on a diet...
See, they used to fight
forjewelry.
They bit his ears.
Finally, I was in a hat shop,
and these are hat bands.
So I said, "Gee,
that'll fit that fatso."
I bought that one
because she looked
just like a client I had,
that kind of a face.
He's a cute little guy.
- Carl!
- What?
- Do you want a cup of tea?
- Do I want a cup of tea?
- Oh, that would be nice.
- You do?
Lemon tea, lots of lemon.
- Albert?
- Yeah.
Would you like
a cup of something?
She's making me some tea.
Good.
ls that okay?
Yeah.